<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/ML/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/ML/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-05-30T01:16:14+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ML/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ML techniques</title><subtitle>This repo contains the solutions of coding interview questions from various sources.
</subtitle><author><name>Bhoomeendra Singh Sisodiy</name></author><entry><title type="html">Logistic Regression</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ML/jekyll/2023-05-08-Logistic_Regression.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Logistic Regression" /><published>2023-05-08T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-05-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ML/jekyll/Logistic_Regression</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ML/jekyll/2023-05-08-Logistic_Regression.html"><![CDATA[<!-- #### What is Logistic Regression? -->

<p>Logistic regression is linear regression over the log odds or logit of the probability of input belonging to a class. The model choice in logistic regression is the logits of the probability are linearly dependent on the independent variable. But the problem we solve with this is the <strong>classification problem</strong>. The output of the model is the probability of the input belonging to a class.
\(logit(p) = log(\frac{p}{p+1})\)</p>

<p>The model is as follows:</p>

\[logit(p) = w^Tx + b\]

\[p = \frac{1}{1+e^{-(w^Tx+b)}}\]

\[p = \sigma(w^Tx+b)\]

<p>What sigmoid does is that it constrains the output between 0 and 1. This is one of the definitions of logistic regression.</p>
<h3 id="geometric-formulation">Geometric Formulation</h3>
<p>We can have a geometric explanation as well. We start with a classification boundary which is \(w^Tx +b\). We want a w such that \(\forall i \; y_i(w^Tx_i+b)&gt;=0\) i.e the predicted class and the actual class are of the same sign for the product term to be positive but using a objective function which maximizes \(\sum y_i(w^Tx_i+b)\) has some limitation. The problem is that when an outlier comes, the loss value will be very high, and the model will try to fit the outlier. To solve the problem sigmoid function is used as it constrains the values between 0 and 1 which limits the impact of outlier.</p>

<h3 id="formulation-of-the-loss-function">Formulation of the loss function</h3>
<p>The purpose of the loss function is to maximize the probability of the correct class. Logistic regression is a binary classification problem; hence we have two classes, 0 and 1. Higher probability is associated with class 1, and low probability is associated with class 0. The objective function is as follows:</p>

\[L = \prod_{i=1}^n p_i^{y_i}(1-p_i)^{1-y_i} \; where \; p = \sigma(w^Tx+b)\]

\[L = \prod_{i=1}^n \sigma(w^Tx_i+b)^{y_i}(1-\sigma(w^Tx_i+b))^{1-y_i}\]

<p>As all the values are always positive, taking log will not affect the optimization problem. Also will help with numerical stability as the probability values are very small and the product will be even smaller. Hence the loss function is as follows:</p>

\[L = \sum_{i=1}^n y_i log(\sigma(w^Tx_i+b)) + (1-y_i)log(1-\sigma(w^Tx_i+b))\]

\[w^* = argmax_w L(w)\]

<p>But still, we have a problem which is that if when w tends to infinity, the we would have the maximum value of the objective function, which is not what we want. Hence we add a regularization term to the objective function. The objective function is as follows:</p>

\[L =  \sum_{i=1}^n y_i log(\sigma(w^Tx_i+b)) + (1-y_i)log(1-\sigma(w^Tx_i+b)) + \lambda ww^T\]

<!-- This theme supports rendering beautiful math in inline and display modes using [MathJax 3](https://www.mathjax.org/) engine. You just need to surround your math expression with `$$`, like `$$ E = mc^2 $$`. If you leave it inside a paragraph, it will produce an inline expression, just like $$ E = mc^2 $$. -->

<!-- To use display mode, again surround your expression with `$$` and place it as a separate paragraph. Here is an example: -->

<!-- $$\sum_{k=1}^\infty |\langle x, e_k \rangle|^2 \leq \|x\|^2$$ -->

<h3 id="interview-questions">Interview Questions</h3>

<p>Should we normailze the data before giving it to the logistice regression algorithim?</p>

<p>Yes we should normalize the data it would give use two problems first is the</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Interpretiblity of the weights/coffecient</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Interpretiblity of the weights/coffecient as because the coffecient indicats the impact on prediction when we have unit change in the feature but feats with differect scale can not be compaired with each other once we normalize (Min Max) or standardize (\(\mu =0 , \sigma =1\)) the data becomes unitless hence comparative interpretblity is possible which could indicate geniune feature importance.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Convergence of SGD</p>

    <ul>
      <li>The magnitude of gradient of depends on the values of the inputs which we can see for both squared loss and cross entorpy loss which mean that feature with higher values wil have bigger gradient and features with smaller values will have smaller gradient hence convergence would led to ossilation but when the data is normalized such problem is prevented.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Bhoomeendra</name></author><category term="Jekyll" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Metrics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ML/jekyll/2023-05-08-Metrics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Metrics" /><published>2023-05-08T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-05-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ML/jekyll/Metrics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ML/jekyll/2023-05-08-Metrics.html"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Bhoomeendra</name></author><category term="Jekyll" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Regularization</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ML/jekyll/2023-05-08-Regularization.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Regularization" /><published>2023-05-08T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-05-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ML/jekyll/Regularization</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ML/jekyll/2023-05-08-Regularization.html"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Bhoomeendra</name></author><category term="Jekyll" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Linear Regression</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ML/jekyll/2023-05-08-Linear-Regression.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Linear Regression" /><published>2023-05-08T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-05-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ML/jekyll/Linear%20Regression</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ML/jekyll/2023-05-08-Linear-Regression.html"><![CDATA[<!-- #### What is Linear Regression? -->
<p>The linear regression establishes a relationship between the dependent variable (y) and one or more independent variables (x) using a best-fit straight line. This means relationship between the dependent and independent variables is linear in nature.</p>

<h4 id="different-ways-to-solve-linear-regression">Different ways to solve Linear Regression</h4>
<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Normal Equation:</strong> The normal equation is a closed-form solution for linear regression (Gaussian Elimination). It finds the value of the regression coefficients that minimizes the sum of the squared residuals.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Gradient Descent:</strong> Gradient descent is an iterative optimization algorithm that can be used to solve linear regression. It works by finding the minimum of a cost function, which is typically the sum of the squared residuals.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Singular Value Decomposition:</strong> The SVD is used because the data matrix is non-invertible hence we calcute its pseudo-inverse using SVD this is a great artricle explaning the same <a href="https://sthalles.github.io/svd-for-regression/">Visit</a>.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h4 id="checks-to-apply-before-applying-linear-regression">Checks to apply before applying Linear Regression</h4>
<ol>
  <li><strong>Linearity:</strong> Linear relationship between dependent and independent variables that can be done using person correlation coefficient not the spearman correlation coefficient.</li>
  <li><strong>Normality:</strong> The residuals are normally distributed. This means that the residuals follow a bell-shaped curve, with most of the values clustered around the mean. The normality assumption is necessary because it allows us to use the standard techniques of statistical inference, such as hypothesis testing and confidence intervals. Violations of normality can lead to biased and inefficient estimates, and incorrect conclusions about the statistical significance of the independent variables.</li>
  <li><strong>Homoscedasticity:</strong> The distribution of residual should be same for all the values of independent variable because if the errors are dependent on the value of independent variable then the model is uncertain as some inputs and is certian at some inputs. This does not provide us a concrete prediction hence the model is not very reiable.</li>
  <li><strong>No multicollinearity:</strong> There is no high correlation between the independent variables. This means that the independent variables are not too closely related to each other.  If there is high correlation between the independent variables, it can be difficult to separate out their individual effects on the dependent variable, leading to unstable estimates of the regression coefficients.</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="how-to-deal-with-multicollinearity">How to deal with multicollinearity?</h4>
<ol>
  <li><strong>Remove one of the correlated variables:</strong> The simplest way to deal with multicollinearity is to remove one of the highly correlated variables from the regression model. The downside of this approach is that it reduces the degrees of freedom of the model, which can weaken the statistical power of your analysis.</li>
  <li><strong>Combine the correlated variables:</strong> Another way to deal with multicollinearity is to combine the correlated variables together to form a single predictor. For example, if you had two highly correlated variables, you could combine them together to form a single predictor by taking their average.</li>
  <li><strong>Use principal components:</strong> Principal components analysis (PCA) is a dimension reduction technique that can be used to reduce a large set of variables to a small set that still contains most of the information in the large set. This technique is useful when you have a large number of correlated predictors, and you want to summarize them with a smaller set of representative variables.</li>
  <li><strong>Use regularization methods:</strong> Regularization methods, such as ridge (L2 regularization) regression and lasso regression( L1 Regularization), are powerful techniques that are designed to deal with multicollinearity by constraining the size of the regression coefficients. These methods work well when you have a large number of correlated predictors.</li>
  <li><strong>Do nothing:</strong> If your goal is to make predictions, and not to understand the role of each individual variable, then multicollinearity might not be a problem. Multicollinearity only affects the interpretation of your model if you care about the specific role of each variable. However, multicollinearity does affect the precision of the estimated regression coefficients, which can cause your predictions to be less reliable.</li>
  <li><strong>Use Partial Least Squares Regression:</strong> Partial least squares regression (PLS regression) is a regression method that is an alternative to ordinary least squares (OLS) regression. PLS regression is useful when you have a large number of correlated predictors, and you want to use them to predict an outcome, but you also want to reduce the number of predictors in your model. PLS regression is similar to principal components regression, but the key difference between the two methods is that PLS regression uses the response variable in the dimension reduction step, while principal components regression does not.</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="what-is-the-difference-between-l1-and-l2-regularization">What is the difference between L1 and L2 regularization?</h4>
<p>L2 regularization is also known as ridge regression. L1 also known as Lasso. The key difference between them is when we take derivative of the loss function for both, In L2 we see the update or change would be 2*coeff but in L1 it would be either 1 or -1. This is the reason why L1 regularization is used for feature selection and drives some of the coefficients to zero. <a href="https://medium.com/@mukulranjan/how-does-lasso-regression-l1-encourage-zero-coefficients-but-not-the-l2-20e4893cba5d">Visit</a></p>

<h1 id="interview-questions">Interview Questions</h1>]]></content><author><name>Bhoomeendra</name></author><category term="Jekyll" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The linear regression establishes a relationship between the dependent variable (y) and one or more independent variables (x) using a best-fit straight line. This means relationship between the dependent and independent variables is linear in nature.]]></summary></entry></feed>